Inventory of O.41 - Collection of Lists and Documentation Regarding Those Who Perished and Those Who Were Persecuted During the Holocaust Period O.41
O.41 - Collection of Lists and Documentation Regarding Those Who Perished and Those Who Were Persecuted During the Holocaust Period
date empty
Paper, 6 meters Paper, 1301 files List of persecuted persons List of murdered persons List of deportees List of inmates List of camp inmates Personal documents List of Jewish soldiers List of Jewish residents List of survivors Death certificate Photograph
Yad Vashem
O.41
O.41 - Collection of Lists and Documentation Regarding Those Who Perished and Those Who Were Persecuted During the Holocaust Period The collection is mainly comprised of lists of Jews who perished or were persecuted during the Holocaust period. These lists come from many diverse sources, various types and different languages. The lists of those who perished were compiled and prepared by official sources and established bodies, as well as by family members, friends and fellow townspeople. Besides the lists of those who perished, the Collection also contains concurrent lists of those who were deported and persecuted, i. e. lists compiled during World War II in the camps and in the ghettos. Additionally, there are lists that were constructed during the early days after the liberation and through the late 1990s. A large number of the lists were prepared and compiled in order to commemorate and memorialize; they reflect the strong desire of the survivors to preserve the memory of those who perished. In the various lists there is diverse information regarding those who perished and those who were persecuted besides their names. In the Collection, there are also many certificates and authorizations issued by various organizations throughout Europe at the request of close family members and friends searching for their loved ones after the war. These certificates and authorizations provide information regarding their fate during the Holocaust. This record group can be described as a database of scores of thousands of names of Jews who perished or were persecuted during the Holocaust.
- Declaration by Klara Fedyuk, regarding her detention in the Slutzk Ghetto and her escape, 08/02/1943 and regarding the fate of Israel and Khaya Yevelev, who were murdered in the ghetto, 21/04/1990-21/04/1990; 1 Personal documents Declaration Record of survivors Record of murdered persons xerox; O.41/552
  Slutsk,Ghetto
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by יווילב זכר
  Declaration by Klara Fedyuk, regarding her detention in the Slutzk Ghetto and her escape, 08/02/1943 and regarding the fate of Israel and Khaya Yevelev, who were murdered in the ghetto
- List of Jews in the Korelicze Ghetto, 20/05/1942, Спис населения гетто Кореличи по состоянию на 20 мая 1942 года; 20/05/1942-20/06/1942; 54 List of ghetto inmates xerox; O.41/521
  Korelicze,Nowogrodek,Nowogrodek,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by כהן דב
  List of Jews in the Korelicze Ghetto, 20/05/1942
  The list/s contain approximately 888 names
- Draft order to forced labor received by Martin Dawer, from Mogilev, 09/05/1942, and confirmation by the Romanian authorities regarding his deportation, issued after the war, date empty; 3 Certification Record of survivors xerox; O.41/549
  Mogilev Podolski,Mogilev Podolskiy City,Vinnitsa,Ukraine (USSR)
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by דאבר מרטין
  Draft order to forced labor received by Martin Dawer, from Mogilev, 09/05/1942, and confirmation by the Romanian authorities regarding his deportation, issued after the war
- Section from a list of Jews deported from Berlin to Lodz, 01/11/1941, date empty; 6 List of deportees Typewritten copy; O.41/477
  Berlin,Berlin,Berlin,Germany; Lodz,Lodz,Lodz,Poland
  Section from a list of Jews deported from Berlin to Lodz, 01/11/1941
  The list/s contain approximately 90 names
- Death certificate of Lea Cherqui, born in Alger (Algiers), who perished in Majdanek, 30/03/1943, 09/07/1959-09/07/1959; The file was created by Mairie du 18 Arrondissement; 2 Personal documents Death certificate Record of murdered persons Original; O.41/508
  Paris,Seine,<>,France; Majdanek,Camp,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by גדז' בטי יעקב
  Death certificate of Lea Cherqui, born in Alger (Algiers), who perished in Majdanek, 30/03/1943
- Section from a list of inmates transferred from Kamenz camp to Dachau, 16/03/1945, date empty; 2 List of camp inmates List of inmates Typewritten; O.41/481
  Kamenz,Camp; Dachau,Camp,Germany
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by Konieczny Alfred
  Section from a list of inmates transferred from Kamenz camp to Dachau, 16/03/1945
  The list/s contain approximately 115 names
- Confirmation by the ITS that Liuba Goldberg, from Kowno, stayed in Stutthof camp, 17/07/1944, 12/10/1981-12/10/1981; 2 Personal documents Certification Record of survivors Typewritten copy; O.41/472
  Stutthof,Camp; Kowno,Kaunas,<>,Lithuania
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by נוסליס חנה-לובה
  Confirmation by the ITS that Liuba Goldberg, from Kowno, stayed in Stutthof camp, 17/07/1944
- Documentation issued by the ITS, regarding the fate of Chaim Lajb Ajzenberg, born in Lodz, Poland, a resident of Berlin who perished in Ahlem camp, 07/12/1944, 28/05/1956-24/09/1984; 4 Personal documents Death certificate Certification Record of murdered persons xerox; O.41/496
  Lodz,Lodz,Lodz,Poland; Berlin,Berlin,Berlin,Germany; Ahlem,Camp,Germany; ITS - International Tracing Service
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by ברגבאום י
  Documentation issued by the ITS, regarding the fate of Chaim Lajb Ajzenberg, born in Lodz, Poland, a resident of Berlin who perished in Ahlem camp, 07/12/1944
- Documentation issued by the ITS, regarding the fate of Zalman Einhorn, born in Ganya, Czechoslovakia, who perished in Buchenwald camp, 09/09/1944, date empty; 3 Personal documents Death certificate Record of murdered persons Certification xerox; O.41/485
  Ganya,Tacovo,Carpathian Ruthenia,Czechoslovakia; Buchenwald,Camp; ITS - International Tracing Service
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by מאיר טובה
  Documentation issued by the ITS, regarding the fate of Zalman Einhorn, born in Ganya, Czechoslovakia, who perished in Buchenwald camp, 09/09/1944
- List of Jews from Esztergom, who perished 1944-1945, based on the monument erected in memory of the local Holocaust victims, 28/06/1949-28/06/1949; 6 List of murdered persons xerox; O.41/40
  Monuments; Commemoration; Esztergom,Esztergom,<>,Hungary
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by Schatz Odon
  List of Jews from Esztergom who perished, 1944-1945, based on the monument erected in memory of the local Holocaust victims The list also contains the names of those in the labor battalions (p. 1057) who perished. The file also contains a letter of thanks written by the chairperson of the Hungarian Jewish Communities Committee in 1949 to the person who submitted the material, Oedoen Schatz, thanking him for his efforts in memorializing those who perished.
  The list/s contain approximately 516 names
- List of Icchak Strulovitz's family members from Chust district, who perished, 1942-1945, מצבת זכרון על בני משפחתי ועל כל בית-ישראל שנספו בשואת יהודי אירופה; 12/02/1966-12/02/1966; The file was created by Icchak Strulovitz; 2 List of murdered persons Survey Typewritten original; O.41/43
  Nizni Bystry,Chust,Carpathian Ruthenia,Czechoslovakia; <>,Chust,Carpathian Ruthenia,Czechoslovakia; Zadne,Irsava,Carpathian Ruthenia,Czechoslovakia; Koseli,Chust,Carpathian Ruthenia,Czechoslovakia
  List of Icchak Strulovitz's family members from Chust district, who perished, 1942-1945 The file also contains a brief review of what happened to the Jews who lived in the villages near Chust during the Holocaust.
  The list/s contain approximately 16 names
- List of Jews from Mszana Dolna, prepared by the Germans, 15/06/1942, with the names of the Jews murdered, 19/08/1942, and buried in a mass grave in Mszana Dolna indicated, רשימת הקרבנות שנקברו בקבר אחים במשאנא דולנה (פולין); Spis pochowanych w grobie masowym we Mszanie Dolnej; 15/06/1942-15/06/1942; The file was created by יוסף בן שמואל גולדברגר; 23 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/22
  Mszana Dolna,Limanowa,Krakow,Poland; Mszana Dolna,Murder Site
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by יהודה וייסברגר
  List of Jews from Mszana Dolna, prepared by the Germans, 15/06/1942, with the names of the Jews murdered, 19/08/1942, and buried in a mass grave in Mszana Dolna indicated List includes the names of 881 Jews murdered in Mszana Dolna, 19/08/1942 and buried in a mass grave in Mszana Dolna, as well as the names of other Jews from Mszana Dolna and the Mszana Dolna area who were deported to labor camps, mainly to a quarry in Limanova where most of the deportees perished.
  The list/s contain approximately 1029 names
- List of Jews from Sileul Silvanei who were deported in 1944, submitted by Elly Gross, 1998-1998; 17 List of deportees List of murdered persons List of survivors List of persecuted persons xerox; O.41/924
  Simleul Silvaniei,Salaj,Transylvania,Romania; Auschwitz,Camp,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by Gross Elly
  List of Jews from Sileul Silvanei who were deported in 1944, submitted by Elly Gross.
  The list/s contain approximately 1300 names
- List of Jews from Osterholz Scharmbeck, including their experiences during the Holocaust and additional documentation, date empty; 5 List of deportees Record of survivors List of murdered persons Article xerox; O.41/923
  Osterholz Scharmbeck,<>,Hanover,Germany
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by Ernst-Goergens Birgit, Goergens Harald
  List of Jews from Osterholz Scharmbeck, including their experiences during the Holocaust and additional documentation
  - List of Jews from Osterholz-Scharmbeck and their fate during the Holocaust, date empty; 2 List of deportees Record of survivors List of murdered persons; O.41/923.1
    List of Jews from Osterholz-Scharmbeck and their fate during the Holocaust
    The list/s contain approximately 46 names
- List of Jews from Cakovec who perished during the Holocaust, 1941-1945, prepared by Moshe Gruenwald Etz-Khaim, 1977-1977; The file was created by משה עץ-חיים גרינוולד; 7 List of murdered persons xerox; O.41/72
  Cakovec,<>,Croatia Transmura,Yugoslavia
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by הירשזון לדיסלב
  List of Jews from Cakovec who perished during the Holocaust, 1941-1945, prepared by Moshe Gruenwald Etz-Khaim
  The list/s contain approximately 230 names
- List of Jews from Nieswiez who perished, 1941-1945, רשימת קדושי ניעסוויעזש; 1955-1955; 11 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/9
  Nieswiez,Nieswiez,Nowogrodek,Poland
  List of Jews from Nieswiez who perished, 1941-1945
  The list/s contain approximately 535 names
- List of Jews from Vilna and the Vilna vicinity murdered in Schoemberg camp, 1944-1945, who were buried in the cemetery in Schoemberg, צום אנדענק פון די ווילנער קרבנות אויפן שעמבערג בית-עולם; date empty; The file was created by פארבאנד פון ווילנער יידן אין די פאראייניקטע שאטן; 13 List of murdered persons Survey Original; O.41/6
  Wilno,Wilno,Wilno,Poland; Schoemberg,Camp; Dautmergen,Camp; Wilno,Ghetto
  List of Jews from Vilna and the Vilna vicinity murdered in Schoemberg camp, 1944-1945, who were buried in the cemetery in Schoemberg The list was published by The Vilna Association for Assistance and Rescue, September, 1963. The booklet includes Forwards written by Batia Popka and Mordchai Bernstein who recall the story of hundreds of Jews from Vilna who were brought to the camp and murdered there and the Camp Graveyard where 1,755 Jews who were murdered are buried. The call-out number of the booklet in Yad Vashem Library is 77-0653.
  - List of Jews from Vilna and the Vilna vicinity who perished in Schoemberg camp, 1944-1945, and were buried in the cemetery in Schoemberg, צום אנדענק פון די ווילנער קרבנות אויפן שעמבערג בית-עולם; date empty; 7 List of murdered persons List of camp inmates; O.41/6.1
    List of Jews from Vilna and the Vilna vicinity who perished in Schoemberg (Dautmergen) camp, 1944-1945, and were buried in the cemetery in Schoemberg
    The list/s contain approximately 385 names
- Yizkor book of the Zutphen community, including a list of Jewish residents of Zutphen who perished, 1942-1945; Yizkor book published, 1960, 1960-1960; The file was created by Nederlandse Israelische Gemeente; 16 Yizkor book Letter Photograph List of murdered persons Original; O.41/29
  Commemoration; Monuments; Zutphen,Gelderland,<>,The Netherlands
  Yizkor book of the Zutphen community, including a list of Jewish residents of Zutphen who perished, 1942-1945; Yizkor book published, 1960 Included in the file: - History of the Jewish community of Zutphen; - Photographs of monuments established in commemoration of the victims, 1949.
  - List of Jews from Zutphen who perished, 1942-1945, prepared by the Nederlandse Israelische Gemeente, 1960-1960; 8 List of murdered persons; O.41/29.1
    Zutphen,Gelderland,<>,The Netherlands
    List of Jews from Zutphen who perished, 1942-1945, prepared by the Nederlandse Israelische Gemeente
    The list/s contain approximately 399 names
- List of Jews from Demidowka who perished, 1941-1944, 1955-1955; 13 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/13
  Demidowka,Dubno,Wolyn,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by ש. מיימון
  List of Jews from Demidowka who perished, 1941-1944
  The list/s contain approximately 650 names
- Yizkor Book containing the names of the Jews of the Tornala community who perished, 1944, ספר הזכרון להחברה קדושה דק"ק טארנאלא; date empty; 50 List of murdered Jews Yizkor book Original; O.41/18
  Commemoration; Bequeathing the Holocaust; Tornala,Gemer,Slovakia,Czechoslovakia
  Yizkor Book containing the names of the Jews of the Tornala community who perished, 1944
  The list/s contain approximately 1018 names
- Lists of Jews who were murdered in Opoczno and Zarnow, 1940-1943; lists prepared, 1987, 04/06/1987-04/06/1987; The file was created by Okregowa Komisja BZH Institutu Pamięci Narodowej; 7 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/34
  Opoczno,Opoczno,Kielce,Poland; Zarnow,Opoczno,Kielce,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by הועדה לחקר פשעי הנאצים בלודז'
  Lists of Jews who were murdered in Opoczno and Zarnow, 1940-1943; lists prepared, 1987
  - List of Jews who perished in Opoczno, 1940-1943, Wykaz obywateli polskich narodowości żidowskiej zamordowanych w Opocznie w latach 1940-43; 04/06/1987-04/06/1987; 4 List of murdered persons; O.41/34.1
    Opoczno,Opoczno,Kielce,Poland
    List of Jews who perished in Opoczno, 1940-1943
    The list/s contain approximately 35 names
  - List of Jews who were murdered in Zarnow, 1941-1943, Wykaz obywateli polskich narodowości żidowskiej zamordowanych w Żarnovie w latach 1941-43; 04/06/1987-04/06/1987; 2 List of murdered persons; O.41/34.2
    Zarnow,Opoczno,Kielce,Poland
    List of Jews who were murdered in Zarnow, 1941-1943
    The list/s contain approximately 17 names
- List of the Jews from Rejowiec who perished,1941-1944, date empty; The file was created by ארגון יוצאי רייביץ; 29 List of murdered persons Photograph xerox Print; O.41/37
  Monuments; Commemoration; Rejowiec,Chelm,Lublin,Poland; Kielce pogrom
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by צרליכמן /ארגון יוצאי רייביץ
  List of the Jews from Rejowiec who perished, 1941-1944
  The list/s contain approximately 700 names
- List of 96 inmates from concentration camps who were buried in the cemetery in Pocking, and correspondence regarding cemeteries and mass graves in former concentration camps in Germany, date empty; 21 List of murdered persons Official documentation Newspaper clippings Letter xerox; O.41/23
  Cemeteries; Mass graves; Pocking,Camp; Mettenheim Oberbayern,Oberbayern,Bavaria,Germany; Hersbruck,Oberfranken und Mittelfranken,Bavaria,Germany; Buchenwald,Camp; Flossenbuerg,Camp
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by מועצה מקומית מטולה
  List of 96 inmates from concentration camps who were buried in the cemetery in Pocking, and correspondence regarding cemeteries and mass graves in former concentration camps in Germany
  - List of 96 prisoners who were buried in the Pocking camp cemetery, date empty; 3 List of murdered persons List of camp inmates; O.41/23.1
    Pocking,Camp
    List of 96 prisoners who were buried in the Pocking camp cemetery
    The list/s contain approximately 97 names
- List of Jews from Gliniany who perished, 1941-1944, טויטן -ליסטע פון קדושים פון דעם שטעטל גלינע בעצירק פרעמישליאן ביי לבוב גאליציא; 1955-1955; The file was created by שלמה נוסבאום-שפייזער; 81 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/3
  Gliniany,Przemyslany,Tarnopol,Poland
  List of Jews from Gliniany who perished1941-1944 The list was prepared by Shlomo Nussbaum-Speiser from Haifa based on lists submitted by Avraham Schlumpier from Raanana and materials appearing in the "Gliniany Scroll" edited by Hanoch Halperin from New York.
  The list/s contain approximately 1451 names
- Lists of Jews from Neuwied who perished in the Holocaust, including additional documentation, date empty; 28 Personal documents Certification List of murdered persons Photograph xerox; O.41/887
  Neuwied,Koblenz,Rhine Province,Germany
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by Wuest Rolf
  Lists of Jews from Neuwied who perished in the Holocaust, including additional documentation Also in the file: - Death certificates of Max and Liesel Fenig and Rosel Loewenstein, residents of Neuwied, Germany who were deported [from Germany?] and perished.
  - List of Jews from Neuwied who perished during the Holocaust, date empty; 23 Card file List of murdered persons; O.41/887.1
    List of Jews from Neuwied who perished during the Holocaust
    The list/s contain approximately 28 names
- List of Jews from Tarnogrod who perished during the Holocaust, date empty; 27 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/971
  Tarnogrod,Bilgoraj,Lublin,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by בורנשטיין חיים
  List of Jews from Tarnogrod who perished during the Holocaust
  The list/s contain approximately 1895 names
- Documentation regarding the transfer of the remains of inmates from Bremen and Obernheide camps from the Riensberger cemetery to the Osterholz [cemetery] in Bremen, 1956; documentation dated, 1954-1956, 1954-1956; 15 Official documentation List of camp inmates List of murdered persons Reports Newspaper clippings xerox; O.41/10
  Bremen,Camp,Germany; Bremen,Bremen,Bremen,Germany; Obernheide,Camp,Germany
  Documentation regarding the transfer of the remains of inmates from Bremen and Obernheide camps from the Riensberger cemetery to the Osterholz [cemetery] in Bremen, 1956; documentation dated, 1954-1956
  - List of prisoners who perished in Obernheide camp, and whose ashes were buried in the Jewish cemetery in Bremen, 1956, 28/01/1956-28/01/1956; 5 List of murdered persons List of camp inmates; O.41/10.1
    Obernheide,Camp,Germany; Bremen,Bremen,Bremen,Germany
    The list/s contain approximately 170 names
- List of Jews from Tarnow who perished during the Holocaust, date empty; 24 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/889
  Tarnow,Tarnow,Krakow,Poland
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by יוסף קורנילו
  List of Jews from Tarnow who perished during the Holocaust
  The list/s contain approximately 1985 names
- List of Jews from Denmark who were deported to Theresienstadt 06/10/1943, and died there, Namen der Juden, die von Daenemark im Oktober 1943 nach Theresienstadt deportiert wurden und dort gestorben sind.; 21/04/1955-21/04/1955; The file was created by יוליוס מרגולינסקי; 4 List of deportees List of murdered persons Original; O.41/7
  <>,<>,<>,Denmark; Theresienstadt,Ghetto,Czechoslovakia; Transport XXV/2 from <>,<>,<>,Denmark to Theresienstadt,Ghetto,Czechoslovakia
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by Julius Margolinsky
  List of Jews from Denmark who were deported to Theresienstadt 06/10/1943, and died there
  The list/s contain approximately 55 names
- Pocket diary with a list of 94 Jews who died in a cattle car during their transfer to Bergen-Belsen, 04/1945 and who were buried in the cemetery in Troebitz after the liberation, 05/1945, 02/05/1945-02/05/1945; The file was created by מאיר; 78 Diary Newspaper clippings List of murdered Jews Original; O.41/30
  Mass burial; Holocaust survivors; Survivors organizations; Troebitz,Frankfurt,Brandenburg,Germany; Bergen Belsen,Camp,Germany; Liberation - Red Army
  Pocket diary with a list of 94 Jews who died in a cattle car during their transfer to Bergen-Belsen, 04/1945 and who were buried in the cemetery in Troebitz after the liberation, 05/1945 Included in the file: - Newspaper clipping from "The Miami News", May 1985, about the owner of the diary Meir, a Holocaust survivor of Bergen-Belsen, who buried the Jews who died in the cattle car in the cemetery in Troebitz: Meir wrote in his diary the names of the people who died.
  - List of 94 Jews who perished in a cattle car in which they were transported to Bergen-Belsen, 04/1945 [apparently due to a typhus epidemic that broke out in the railroad car], and who were buried in the cemetery in Troeblitz after the liberation, 05/1945, 02/05/1945-02/05/1945; 4 List of murdered Jews; O.41/30.1
    Troebitz,Frankfurt,Brandenburg,Germany; Bergen Belsen,Camp,Germany
    List of 94 Jews who perished in a cattle car in which they were transported to Bergen-Belsen, 04/1945 [apparently due to a typhus epidemic that broke out in the railroad car], and who were buried in the cemetery in Troeblitz after the liberation, 05/1945
    The list/s contain approximately 94 names
- Photograph of a monument in Bordeaux engraved with the names of Jews who perished, date empty; 3 List of murdered persons Original; O.41/14
  Bequeathing the Holocaust; Commemoration; Monuments; Bordeaux,Gironde,<>,France
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by טוביה פרידמן
  Photograph of a monument in Bordeaux engraved with the names of Jews who perished
  The list/s contain approximately 588 names
- List of Jewish residents from the Podborany district some of whom were deported to the death camps where they perished, Landsleute mosaischen Glaubens im Heimatkreis Podersam - Jechnitz, Boehmen; 1988-1988; The file was created by Karl Woda; 9 List of murdered persons List of deportees Article Original; O.41/27
  Podersam,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Jechnitz,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Kriegern,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Schaar,Podersam,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Scheles,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Wallisgruen,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Woratschen,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Neuwallisdorf,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Oberklee,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Schmihof,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Schoenhof,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Sossen,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Welhotten,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia; Wilkau,Podborany,Bohemia,Czechoslovakia
  List of Jewish residents from the Podborany district some of whom were deported to the death camps where they perished
  The list/s contain approximately 144 names
- Letter regarding the desecration of the cemetery in Pyskowice where people who were murdered in the camps were buried; letter written by A. Caransa, from Amsterdam, 1981, 20/04/1981-20/04/1981; 5 Letter Stencil; O.41/41
  Jewish cemeteries; Pyskowice,Oppeln,Silesia (Upper),Germany; Amsterdam,Noordholland,<>,The Netherlands
  The materials were transferred to Yad Vashem by אינג'. א. קאראנסה, אמסטרדם, הולנד